Eric Wetzel

Austin, Texas 78759 | 512-751-6182 ewetzel@gmail.com | ericwetzel.com | linkedin.com/in/ewetzel | github/sonder74

Summary

I am a communications professional, content producer, and creative project manager with a background in writing, fundraising, and computer programming. I simplify complex information into narratives for donors, the public, and other audiences. I also have experience working with cross-functional teams and am certified in data analysis and visualization by The University of Texas at Austin.

Experience

Founder and Principal | Wetzel & Company | Austin | 2016 - Current

- Provide strategic communications, fundraising, technical writing, video production, social-media
 management, and content marketing services to clients that have included nonprofit organizations,
 major law firms, North America's largest credential-evaluation service, Baylor University's
 entrepreneur-in-residence, candidates for statewide and local office, and others
- Recruit and manage teams of up to 10 web developers, software engineers, graphic designers, search engine optimization (SEO) specialists, data providers, filmmakers, and direct-mail vendors
- Manage donor-communication campaign for a Texas-based affordable-housing organization with 50,000 subscribers, raising and allocated hundreds of thousands of dollars over five years
- Served as senior communications advisor to 2018 Texas Attorney General candidate Justin Nelson, who came within 3.6 percentage points of victory

Vice President of Communications | Shipley & Associates, Inc. | Austin | 2012 - 2016

- Directly supervised and mentored up to 15 communications and researchers at award-winning public affairs agency specializing in advocacy consulting, crisis management, and media relations
- Managed accounts belonging to members of the Fortune Global 50 and Fortune 500, gubernatorial candidates, major law firms, trade associations, and the ninth-largest political donor in the nation
- Served as spokesperson and led to positive client coverage in *The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal, The Washington Post*, CNN, *USA Today*, Bloomberg News, Politico, *BusinessWeek*, HuffPost, and other major news outlets, driving legal verdicts and settlements totaling more than \$1 billion

Communications Director | Shipley & Associates, Inc. | Austin | 2004 – 2012

- Placed hundreds of media stories on behalf of a technology firm engaged in litigation with 70 major financial institutions, leading to more than \$500 million in legal verdicts, settlements, and royalties
- Wrote proposals that won client contracts worth hundreds of thousands of dollars and annual reports for a \$350 million foundation, successfully managing grantee relations

Editor | West Egg Communications, Inc. | New York | 1997 – 2003

- Served as one of the initial editors and writers at *Book* and *Sea Ray Living*, a pair of national consumer magazines covering the publishing and boating industries
- Successfully positioned *Book* as an acquisition target to Barnes & Noble, grew its circulation to 1.4 million, and helped it win a National Magazine Award
- Managed more than 20 staffers and freelancers and project budgets of \$20,000 or greater
- Interviewed bestselling authors and wrote and edited news stories, features, and more

Skills

Microsoft 365 and Other Basics

Microsoft Word, Microsoft Excel, Microsoft PowerPoint, Microsoft Teams, Microsoft Outlook, Google Docs, Google Sheets, Slack, Grammarly, OpenAI/GPT-4, Associated Press (AP) Style

• Email Marketing and Media Relations

Mailchimp, Mailjet, ActionNetwork, A/B Testing, Prowly, Muck Rack, Business Wire, PR Newswire, EIN Presswire

• Digital Marketing, Web Design, and Web Applications

WordPress, Canva, Search Engine Optimization (SEO) Management, HyperText Markup Language (HTML), Cascading Style Sheets (CSS), JavaScript, Bootstrap, AJAX, Flask, Amazon Web Services (AWS)

• Database Management and Data Interchange

Microsoft Excel, Structured Query Language (SQL), PostgreSQL, SQLite, JavaScript Object Notation (JSON), Application Program Interface (API), MongoDB, Amazon Simple Storage Service (Amazon S3), Apache Hadoop

Data Visualization

Tableau, Plotly, Matplotlib, Leaflet, D3.js, Dashboard Setup and Maintenance

Programming and Data Processing

Python, Pandas, Jupyter Notebooks, NumPy, SciPy, Visual Basic for Applications (VBA)

Web Scraping

Beautiful Soup, Selenium

• Machine Learning

Multiple Linear Regression, Logistic Regression, Random Forests, Neural Networks, TensorFlow, K-Means Clustering, Scikit-Learn

Education

Bachelor of Arts in English, Trinity University | San Antonio Senior Seminars, St. John's College, University of Oxford | Oxford, England

Certifications

Certificate in Data Analysis and Visualization | McCombs School of Business, The University of Texas at Austin | 2020 - 2021

Board Memberships

Board of Directors | The Center for Austin Independent Journalism | 2019 - 2023 Board of Directors | Austin Bat Cave | 2012 Advisory Council | School of Information, The University of Texas at Austin | 2009 - 2010 Board of Directors | Friends of Barton Springs Pool | 2008 - 2009